<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Deliberate Practice | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/deliberate-practice/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-30T02:37:18-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate Practice in Action]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/a-pithy-example-of-deliberate-practice/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-15T00:46:52-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/15/a-pithy-example-of-deliberate-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Wiser and more experienced writers than Bro Kaizen are considering Deliberate Practice, about which I began <a href="(/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/)">harping</a> earlier this week. Here’s perhaps the pithiest example of DP I’ve ever heard described—this is the whole thing in a nutshell.</p>

<!--more-->

<p><blockquote><p>Consider the activity of two basketball players practicing free throws for one hour. Player A shoots 200 practice shots, Player B shoots 50. The Player B retrieves his own shots, dribbles leisurely and takes several breaks to talk to friends. Player A has a colleague who retrieves the ball after each attempt. The colleague keeps a record of shots made. If the shot is missed the colleague records whether the miss was short, long, left or right and the shooter reviews the results after every 10 minutes of practice. To characterize their hour of practice as equal would hardly be accurate. Assuming this is typical of their practice routine and they are equally skilled at the start, which would you predict would be the better shooter after only 100 hours of practice?</p><footer><strong>—Aubrey Daniels</strong></footer></blockquote></p>

<p>The quote is brazenly stolen from <a href="http://aubreydaniels.com/pmezine/expert-performance-apologies-dr-ericsson-it-not-10000-hours-deliberate-practice">here</a>. What could I possibly add to that? </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T22:11:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re overweight, you don’t earn physical fitness by spending three days doing a cardio circuit with your roomate, two days following a diet that your girlfriend invented, four days with Mark Rippetoe’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rippetoe">Starting Strength</a>, and then going to sit on the couch. A piecemeal (and half-heartedly implemented) approach like that is <strong>destined to fail.</strong></p>

<p>But fear not—there is a better way:</p>

<!--more-->

<p>The better approach is called “deliberate practice,” a term that I have shamelessly stolen from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Colvin">Geoff Colvin</a>, <a href="http://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice">James Clear</a>, and <a href="http://www.artofmanliness.com/2010/11/07/the-secret-of-great-men-deliberate-practice/">others</a>. </p>

<p>Deliberate practice has been exhaustively defined and elaborated upon elsewhere (there are literally books written on the topic—follow those links above!) so it wouldn’t make sense to beat a dead horse here. Suffice it to say that deliberate practice is something you must do in order to achieve time-efficient improvements in whatever fields are relevant to your life. In fact, participating in deliberate practice is such a strong predictor of success in a variety of athletic and intellectual fields (even chess!) that it has been called an “unfair advantage.” Needless to say, at this blog, we try to deploy the maximum possible quantity of unfair advantages in your favor. </p>

<p>Let’s construct a short working definition of deliberate practice by examining its attributes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>DP is goal driven, ie. is working towards some objective (bowling 70 km per hour in cricket consistently/learning 100 Pashto words per week/whatever)</li>
  <li>DP involves breaking complex tasks down into tiny, mechanical chunks that <a href="/things-that-take-no-talent">require no talent</a> ie. 1) Sit in your chair in a silent room, 2) load Rosetta Stone software, 3) Repeat Pashto phrases back to the computer for 1 hour, etc. Each of those could easily be done by a very stupid person, who would balk utterly if I commanded him to “Learn Pashto!”</li>
  <li>DP is repeatable, ie. you can come back tomorrow and learn more Pashto vocabulary using the same (sit » load software » repeat words) algorithm as you used today</li>
  <li>DP involves a tight iterative feedback loop, where good or bad outcomes are connected to your actions in near real time. For example, the Rosetta Stone software will grade your pronunciation as soon as you finish talking.</li>
  <li>DP is difficult</li>
</ul>

<p>Deliberate practice is one of this blog’s foundational ideas, and I return to it with a tiresome frequency—so apologies in advance for standing on my soapbox.</p>

<p>In a way, DP is a method for standardizing disparate problem domains. Rather than discovering a new meta-method for every sphere of your life, you can try to make the problem fit a DP shaped mold. Do you need to learn node.js for a project at work? </p>

<ul>
  <li>Find a practice problem that you can solve in Node
    <ul>
      <li>Goal = Use node.js to display the average temperature in London each day on a computer screen</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Break this goal into little chunks. Steps =
    <ul>
      <li>Learn to display “Hello World” on a computer screen</li>
      <li>Find a data source for the temperature. Maybe Her Majesty’s weather service, or weather.com?</li>
      <li>Learn to perform addition and division in Node</li>
      <li>Use addition and division operations at the same time to calculate the average temperature</li>
      <li>Employ each of the previous steps in a single program</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Scale up and repeat
    <ul>
      <li>Now show a timeseries plot of London’s temperature.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Carefully observe the code’s failures and successes. Make note of approaches that did and didn’t work for future use.</li>
  <li>Be prepared for difficulty</li>
</ul>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
