<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: College Advice | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/college-advice/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-06T20:02:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Throw Away Your Television]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T14:57:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Who are we to argue with Anthony Kiedis, former mostly-nude drug addled madman extraordinaire, Red Hot Chili Peppers jefe, and sometime Freddy Mercury lookalike? 

<!--more-->

The Chilis&#8217; classic early aught&#8217;s [pop-rock jam](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xLkD7V07f_E) exhorts listeners to &#8220;throw away your television&#8221; with an argument that boils down to &#8220;reruns are boring.&#8221; This is true but misleading, because there are far better reasons to free yourself from the telly&#8217;s suffocating embrace. 

<span class='caption-wrapper'><img class='caption' src='/images/keidis.jpeg' width='' height='' title='Fig. 1: Mr. Kiedis is recognized as the undisputed world cruiserweight champion of Freddie Mercury impersonators. [^2]'><span class='caption-text'>Fig. 1: Mr. Kiedis is recognized as the undisputed world cruiserweight champion of Freddie Mercury impersonators. [^2]</span></span> 

## I. Creation of Unhealthy Norms

Television is an instrument of state and corporate-industrial-complex propaganda, which therefore promulgates a worldview conducive to the best interests of your society&#8217;s powerful institutions and groups. In many cases, this worldview will explicitly contradict your best interests as a man. If you expose yourself to the persistent socialization shown on sitcoms, the news, popular dramas, etc, your mentality will begin to bend towards the television&#8217;s unstated premise in a subtle and insidious fashion. There are very few truly iconoclastic role models and lifestyles shown on television today, and a near-total absence of ideas about how to live one&#8217;s life devoted to something other than consuming the maximum possible quantities of industrial products. [^1] 

In other words, the Sultan will never suggest that you develop the skills to disrupt his economic system and thereby become independently wealthy, remove yourself from his low-paid labour force, and use your newfound free time to seduce his harem.

## II. Observe Your Elders
Likely very few of the men you respect spend much time watching TV. If they do, it&#8217;s probably live sports or a single show on DVD/Netflix. For example, Bro Kaizen&#8217;s grandfather spends the overwhelming majority of his time reading, writing his memoirs, working in public service, and tooling around in his garden. He watches a single 30-minute programme, once per week&#8212;and this is a man with limited mobility and significant health problems, for whom it would surely be physically very comfortable to descend into a couch-potato existence of grim daytime soap-opera viewing.

Observe several exceptional men&#8212;most of them spend far less time in front of the television than the median male. This is not a cooincidence. One of Bro Kaizen&#8217;s modern role models, Arnold Schwarzenegger[^3], has the following to say about learning from your elders.

<blockquote><p>&#8220;My father was a country police officer. All he knew was discipline, performance, and work&#8212;not wasting your time. He came from an era where everything was scarce, so everything had to be useful&#8230; But it was from him that I got my work ethic.&#8221;</p></blockquote>

He also touches on time wasting, as per section III below. You&#8217;ll notice that at no point does he advocate sitting around lazily in front of the TV. The quote is borrowed from an interview in [Esquire](http://www.esquire.com/features/what-ive-learned/meaning-of-life-2013/arnold-schwarzenegger-quotes-0113), which contains a few of Arnold&#8217;s other _bon mots._ 


## III. Money, time, and Passivity
Television is expensive. The hardware costs might run to the high hundreds or low thousands of Euros for a big flat-panel display, and cable television costs in some countries as much as hundreds of Euros per month for a upper-middle tier package. You have better things to do with this money&#8212;such as investing it in appreciating assets that will contribute to your eventual financial independence. 

Notably, the dollar costs mentioned above do not account for the time costs of a TV habit. Overwhelmingly large piles of money have been spent to sculpt most programmes into expertly crafted attention magnets. It becomes progressively more difficult to extricate yourself from a series&#8217; plotline and psychological effects once you&#8217;ve let it into your life. It will suck your hours away and you will barely notice they&#8217;re gone. 

Lastly, consider the most pernicious effect of the television-watching lifestyle: chronic indolence. Television watching is designed to beget more television watching, and a weekend spent pissing away time on the sofa will [sap your gumption](http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/) more than any other experience. This effect is particularly dangerous because gumption is a man&#8217;s most precious resource.&#8221;

## IV. Exceptions and Counterpoint

We can also play the hypotheticals game&#8212;if Odysseus were alive today, would you find him parked in front of Modern Family? What about Michel de Montaigne? Winston Churchill? Obviously not.

Naturally there are counterexamples, and it isn&#8217;t hard to imagine the immortal bard savoring a laugh at Basil Fawlty&#8217;s expense or the often bawdy Chaucer relishing the unsubtle innuendos of Jersey Shore. But it is a stretch to propose that those men would make TV their primary passtime.

And of course if TV is a bonding experience with your buddies, the TV time becomes something of a different animal. Male friendships are extremely important, and you must work to nurture them. But if all your friends do is lounge around and watch TV, you might need to re-evaluate the company you keep. 

	
[^1]: Parts of the religious media promulgate a broadly nonmaterialist ideology, but by the anthropic principle, any religious organization wealthy and powerful enough to control significant mindshare on broadcast television or the internet will replace commercial TV&#8217;s mantra of &#8220;Buy consumer goods!&#8221; with one similar in all but name, which might be summarized as &#8220;Pay your tithes and become tightly integrated into our religious organization&#8217;s social structure!&#8221;

[^2]: Image courtesy of the fine folks at [Stadium-Arcadium.com](http://stadium-arcadium.com/04-02-2012/look-around-interactive-music-video-behind-the-scenes-part-three/red-hot-chili-peppers-news/article16224/attachment/anthony-kiedis-look-around-interactive-music-video-red-hot-chili-peppers-im-with-you-rhcp-0202), a startlingly exhaustive RHCP fan site. 

[^3]: All the usual caveats apply about Arnold&#8217;s abysmal acting abilities and thick accent. But he stands in the first tier of men who have done difficult things well and bettered themselves significantly in the process.]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instruction in Natural Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T14:31:02-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[In many college classes and in the knowledge-work industry, you will be required to learn new material from a book. Very likely you will be assigned some reading on the topic, and this reading will probably be from an eminent and respectable tome. When people see you carrying around that tome, or reading it on the tube, they will be quite impressed by your powerful brain. But there's one large drawback.

<!--more-->

<span class='pullquote-right' data-pullquote='the vital concept in chapter 8 was defined exactly once, four hundred pages ago, in chapter 1.'>
That tome will be utterly unhelpful, written in a language of dense jargon, and of the expectation that you will read the accursed thing from cover to cover in its entirety and with a perfect memory, because the vital concept in chapter 8 was defined exactly once, four hundred pages ago, in chapter 1. Furthermore the location of that definition is not mentioned in chapter 8. Such books are peerless when you _already understand_ the topic and aim to deepen your comprehension. But they are the curse of unproductive death for the novice. The paradigmatic example of this is Gleason and Gordon&#8217;s [_Applied Calculus_](http://www.amazon.com/Applied-Calculus-Deborah-Hughes-Hallett/dp/0470170522), which is often assigned to undergraduates in a calculus course for students who are not mathematics majors. These students would do _overwhelmingly_ better to ignore the (needlessly and insultingly expensive) Gleason and Gordon and instead pick up a text written in natural language for a non-specialist audience. In this case, the best answer is something like [_The Complete Idiot&#8217;s Guide to Calculus_](http://www.amazon.com/Complete-Idiots-Guide-Calculus-Edition/dp/1592574718/ref=dp_ob_title_bk). 
</span>

Nobody will be impressed in the slightest when they see you carrying that around. In fact, you&#8217;ll likely be mocked. For this reason, your manager will never hand you a _For Dummies_ or similar title after asking you to figure out a new topic&#8212;it would imply that his company is filled with wankers. Not one professor in all of academia has ever assigned a _Complete Idiot&#8217;s Guide._ But these books are often the most valuable introductory material available anywhere. They assume no prior domain knowledge, tend to treat each chapter as a discrete unit that could be learned alone, are written with many concrete examples, and often include bits of levity to ease the burden of the material&#8217;s density.

Most students feel guilty for ignoring the assigned course text. I hereby give you permission to ignore bad academic material and to make your own decisions about how to optimize learning outcomes. Next time you&#8217;re assigned some dense reading, check to see if you can find a more accessible treatment at one of the following locations or elsewhere:

* [For Dummies](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Dummies), written in a cutesy tone but often quite valuable
* [Complete Idiot&#8217;s guide](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_Idiot%27s_Guides), similarly cutesy, often with groan-inducing humor
* [Better Explained](http://betterexplained.com), which is pure gold
* [The Very Short Introduction Series]( https://global.oup.com/academic/content/series/v/very-short-introductions-vsi/?cc=us&lang=en&), written in a more academic style but generally quite accessible
* [George M. Dallas]( https://georgemdallas.wordpress.com/2014/05/14/wavelets-4-dummies-signal-processing-fourier-transforms-and-heisenberg/), who covers only a handful of technical topics, but does so masterfully.

Caveat: This advice is for the mere mortals who are getting by on elbow grease and long hours. Obviously this does not apply if you&#8217;re a top-5% theoretical thinker. You know who you are. Why are you reading this blog? Go forth and conquer that [special topics seminar in differential geometry](http://maths.anu.edu.au/math3349-special-topics-mathematics-differential-geometry). ]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Maximizing Productivity]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/maximizing-productivity/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-11T18:27:21-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/11/maximizing-productivity</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Napoleon said something like (paraphrasing aggressively here), "The results of every battle are determined ahead of time by the geography, weather, and factors pertaining to the supply of war _materiel_." 

This notion of meta-factors' outsized importance also applies to studying, especially in college.

<!--more-->

When you are studying hard, your brain will become attuned to small details. It is best to point this detail-oriented focus at the text you&#8217;re trying to learn, such as Andrew Ng&#8217;s [Machine Learning course](http://www.holehouse.org/mlclass/) or one of my personal favorite MOOC&#8217;s, _The Theory and Practice of Dodge Diesel Truck Repair for Strongly Heteronormative Men._

In most candidate study locations, there will be a million small distractions that, when compounded, will significantly diminish your focus. Do not waste your mental _oomph_ on small blinking lights on the back of an HP Elitebook&#8217;s NIC, loud IT managers, people walking in your field of view, etc. It is _so important_ to find somewhere with very few audiovisual distractions, where you know you can be productive. 

Instead of taking the first seat in the library that comes into view, you ought to find the single canonically best place to study, and then study there every single time.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
