<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Time Management | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/time-management/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-06T16:20:46-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Throw Away Your Television]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-21T14:57:54-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/21/throw-away-your-television</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[Who are we to argue with Anthony Keidis, former mostly-nude drug addled madman extraordinaire, Red Hot Chili Peppers jefe, and sometime Freddy Mercury lookalike? 

<!--more-->

The Chili&#8217;s classic early aught&#8217;s [pop-rock jam](https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xLkD7V07f_E) exhorts listeners to &#8220;throw away your television&#8221; with an argument that boils down to &#8220;reruns are boring.&#8221; This is true but misleading, because there are far better reasons to free yourself from the telly&#8217;s suffocating embrace. 

<img class="left" src="/images/keidis.jpeg" width="350" height="350" title="re the princes of the uniiii-versssseee" alt="brooooo">

##put image here. Image courtesy of http://stadium-arcadium.com/04-02-2012/look-around-interactive-music-video-behind-the-scenes-part-three/red-hot-chili-peppers-news/article16224/attachment/anthony-kiedis-look-around-interactive-music-video-red-hot-chili-peppers-im-with-you-rhcp-0202



panem et circenses

It is an instrument of state and corporate-industrial-complex propaganda, which therefore promulgates a worldview conducive to the best interests of your society&#8217;s powerful institutions and groups. In many cases, this worldview will explicitly contradict your best interests as a man. If you expose yourself to the persistent socialization shown on sitcoms, the news, popular dramas, etc, your mentality will begin to bend towards the television&#8217;s unstated premise in a subtle and insidious fashion. There are very few truly iconoclastic role models and lifestyles shown on television today, and a near-total absence of ideas about how to live one&#8217;s life devoted to something other than consuming the maximum possible quantities of industrial products. [^1] 

Very few of the men you respect spend much time watching TV. If they do, it&#8217;s probably live sports only.


[^1]: Parts of the religious media promulgate a broadly nonmaterialist ideology, but by the anthropic principle, any religious organization wealthy and powerful enough to control significant mindshare on broadcast television or the internet will replace commercial TV&#8217;s mantra of &#8220;Buy consumer goods!&#8221; with one similar in all but name, which might be summarized as &#8220;Pay your tithes and become tightly integrated into our religious organization&#8217;s social structure!&#8221;]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
