<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Constrained Optimization | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/constrained-optimization/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-30T14:13:27-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Husband Your Gumption]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-17T01:05:07-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/17/husband-your-gumption</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Continuing yesterday’s treatment of <a href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/">gumption and character</a>, it’s time to explicitly highlight an important caveat: Gumption can be depleted! And here too is a chance to connect with Bro Kaizen’s favorite soapbox topic, <a href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/">Deliberate Practice</a>. </p>

<p>Deliberate Practice has 3 inputs:</p>

<!--more-->

<ol>
  <li>Time</li>
  <li>Knowledge</li>
  <li>Gumption</li>
</ol>

<p>Ingredient #1, time management, has been abundantly covered by <a href="http://terrytao.wordpress.com/2008/08/07/on-time-management/">far</a> <a href="http://www.entrepreneur.com/article/220418">greater</a> <a href="http://blog.penelopetrunk.com/2009/01/08/5-time-management-tricks-i-learned-from-years-of-hating-tim-ferriss/">powers</a> than Bro Kaizen. Ingredient #2 has been treated elsewhere, <a href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/12/growth-mentality/">on</a> and <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carol_Dweck">off</a> this blog. Let’s focus on ingredient #3, “Gumption.”</p>

<p>If you expend your gumption fruitlessly, by hours spent copy-and-pasting long columns of figures between Excel spreadsheets, or memorizing vast quantities of facts by rote, you will lack the wherewithal to tackle the design-a-rocket-thruster project when it is offered to you. Similarly, in your drained state, you’ll lack the discipline to stick to your diet, wake up early to visit the gym, man up and go talk to that pretty girl, and avoid the time-wasting temptation of Reddit/Television. Resistance to each of these negative life ingredients draws from the same reservoir.</p>

<p>Therefore you must husband your gumption reserves, protect them from depletion on stupid things, and instead expend them solely on deliberate practice/worthwhile (aka rocket engine design) tasks. You must build a life system wherein positive processes and outcomes happen by default. </p>

<ul>
  <li>Design a trip to the gym into your day (perhaps by joining one between your house and job, such that you pass it every day anyway and you might as well go in). </li>
  <li>Put a pullup bar in your bathroom door so you end up doing a few reps on your way to the shower. (Idea stolen from <a href="http://matt.might.net/articles/hacking-strength/">Matt Might</a>)</li>
  <li>Pay your housemate to withold your wallet and phone every day after work until you complete your 1 hour of Pashto language practice.</li>
</ul>

<p>We want the <em>system</em> to do the heavy motivational lifting/tiresome shlepping automatically, thereby freeing your gumption reservoir for the vital tasks in which it is on the critical path/is the limiting reactant. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
