<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Foundations | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/foundations/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-12-02T01:16:11-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Instruction in Natural Language]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-18T14:31:02-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/18/instruction-in-natural-language</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>In many college classes and in the knowledge-work industry, you will be required to learn new material from a book. Very likely you will be assigned some reading on the topic, and this reading will probably be from an eminent and respectable tome. When people see you carrying around that tome, or reading it on the tube, they will be quite impressed by your powerful brain. But there’s one large drawback.</p>

<!--more-->

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>

<p>Nobody will be impressed in the slightest when they see you carrying that around. In fact, you’ll likely be mocked. For this reason, your manager will never hand you a <em>For Dummies</em> or similar title after asking you to figure out a new topic—it would imply that his company is filled with wankers. Not one professor in all of academia has ever assigned a <em>Complete Idiot’s Guide.</em> But these books are often the most valuable introductory material available anywhere. They assume no prior domain knowledge, tend to treat each chapter as a discrete unit that could be learned alone, are written with many concrete examples, and often include bits of levity to ease the burden of the material’s density.</p>

<p>Most students feel guilty for ignoring the assigned course text. I hereby give you permission to ignore bad academic material and to make your own decisions about how to optimize learning outcomes. Next time you’re assigned some dense reading, check to see if you can find a more accessible treatment at one of the following locations or elsewhere:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/For_Dummies">For Dummies</a>, written in a cutesy tone but often quite valuable</li>
  <li><a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Complete_Idiot%27s_Guides">Complete Idiot’s guide</a>, similarly cutesy, often with groan-inducing humor</li>
  <li><a href="http://betterexplained.com">Better Explained</a>, which is pure gold</li>
  <li><a href="https://global.oup.com/academic/content/series/v/very-short-introductions-vsi/?cc=us&amp;lang=en&amp;">The Very Short Introduction Series</a>, written in a more academic style but generally quite accessible</li>
  <li><a href="https://georgemdallas.wordpress.com/2014/05/14/wavelets-4-dummies-signal-processing-fourier-transforms-and-heisenberg/">George M. Dallas</a>, who covers only a handful of technical topics, but does so masterfully.</li>
</ul>

<p>Caveat: This advice is for the mere mortals who are getting by on elbow grease and long hours. Obviously this does not apply if you’re a top-5% theoretical thinker. You know who you are. Why are you reading this blog? Go forth and conquer that <a href="http://maths.anu.edu.au/math3349-special-topics-mathematics-differential-geometry">special topics seminar in differential geometry</a>. </p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[On Gumption and Character]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-16T02:01:53-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/16/on-gumption-and-character</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Gumption is the gasoline of man’s life. It is the get-up-and-go, the stick-to-it-iveness, and the knocked-down-twice, stand-up-thrice fire inside you. If you run out of it, things will head south very quickly. You must cultivate this gumption, nurture it, and encourage it to grow. Every man possesses by nature a certain rate of gumption replenishment, which rate may be modified by nurture. As you nurture your rate of gumption replenishment, you will also tend to develop in parallel the ability to store more of it. I know of at least two ways to develop gumption:</p>

<!--more-->

<ul>
  <li>Acclimatizing oneself to doing things that are hard (I am blatantly stealing this from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rippetoe">Mark Rippetoe</a>’s book Starting Strength, in the chapter on deadlifts)</li>
  <li>Experiencing deprivation or scarcity</li>
</ul>

<p>There exists a gumption spectrum, upon which we can plot the positions of any given person. For rhetorical purposes, let’s bookend the spectrum with Navy SEALS (the ultra-elite amphibious stormtroopers of the American war machine) on one end, and the decadent, privileged children of the American upper-middle class on the other. (Oddly enough, the real aristocrats have often gone to great lengths to develop their children’s character, even in the most decadent of societies. For this reason there exist scathingly difficult elite boarding schools, summers spent as ranch hands, and dangerous or physics-based hobbies such as Polo and sailboat racing. Witness <a href="http://www.thecrimson.com/article/1957/12/12/theodore-roosevelt-at-harvard-pthe-crimson/">Teddy Roosevelt</a>, a blue blood through and through, and of a character to go toe-to-toe with the best of them. So the social class with the weakest character ends up being the upper-middle.)</p>

<p>Privileged Western white girls/JAP girls are usually typical examples of the no-gumption population, because they have been coddled their whole lives. Their parents have paid for their expensive apartments, unlimited mobile phone plans, vehicles/fuel/insurance, unbelievable quantities of international travel, etc. And if they are <em>hot</em> privileged girls, clueless men have been buying them things/fawning over them/treating them like princesses for many years in a (guaranteed fruitless) attempt to get in their pants. They have experienced neither deprivation nor training in doing hard things, and these missing experiences have eroded/inhibited their character to an alarming degree. (To avoid accusations of hasty generalization, it is worth noting that this is certainly not an accurate description of <em>all</em> privileged Western girls, merely some/many).</p>

<h3 id="how-to-measure-gumption">How to measure gumption:</h3>

<p>Resistance to <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Decision_fatigue">decision fatigue</a> is a good measure of gumption. If you hang out with some rich girls from your school for an afternoon, you’ll quickly realize that some of them can make a median of 2 decisions before becoming pissy and whiny—even trivial choices about which shoes to wear or restaurant/bar to visit wear them out. Conversely, imagine an afternoon spent with a Navy SEAL. He has spent his adult life making literal life-or-death decisions about which grade of armor piercing munitions to load in his helicopter, what rate to expel air from his lungs while submerged in icy saltwater, etc. You could require him to choose restaurants and find his way around a strange city for literally weeks on end (tasks which would incite many tantrums from someone on the other end of the spectrum), and he would not show the slightest sign of feeling pressured. </p>

<p>Naturally, women are not to be found alone on the no-gumption end of the spectrum—there are plenty of weak, insipid men cowering there too, particularly in locales that have insulated the citizenry from deprivation, real work, and difficult tasks. And of course there are women on the SEAL end of the spectrum, as well. The Israelis have done a very impressive job of developing a gender-integrated military, complete with female commandos who demonstrate gumption with the best of them (undoubtedly far more gumption than I will ever possess). </p>

<p>So the point is that gumption is another skill-based-upon-an-aptitude. Each of us is born with a natural level of gumption, but that level can be modified by intentional or unintentional nurture. Your job, as a man, even one in a “soft” society, is to take concious steps to regenerate and store more gumption.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Deliberate Practice]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-14T22:11:59-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>If you’re overweight, you don’t earn physical fitness by spending three days doing a cardio circuit with your roomate, two days following a diet that your girlfriend invented, four days with Mark Rippetoe’s <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Rippetoe">Starting Strength</a>, and then going to sit on the couch. A piecemeal (and half-heartedly implemented) approach like that is <strong>destined to fail.</strong></p>

<p>But fear not—there is a better way:</p>

<!--more-->

<p>The better approach is called “deliberate practice,” a term that I have shamelessly stolen from <a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Geoffrey_Colvin">Geoff Colvin</a>, <a href="http://jamesclear.com/deliberate-practice">James Clear</a>, and <a href="http://www.artofmanliness.com/2010/11/07/the-secret-of-great-men-deliberate-practice/">others</a>. </p>

<p>Deliberate practice has been exhaustively defined and elaborated upon elsewhere (there are literally books written on the topic—follow those links above!) so it wouldn’t do to beat a dead horse at length here. Suffice it to say that deliberate practice is something you must do in order to achieve time-efficient improvements in whatever fields are relevant to your life. In fact, participating in deliberate practice is such a strong predictor of success in a variety of athletic and intellectual fields (even chess!) that it has been called an “unfair advantage.” Needless to say, at this blog, we try to deploy the maximum possible quantity of unfair advantages in your favor. </p>

<p>Let’s construct a short working definition of deliberate practice by examining its attributes:</p>

<ul>
  <li>DP is goal driven, ie. is working towards some objective (bowling 70 km per hour in cricket consistently/learning 100 Pashto words per week/whatever)</li>
  <li>DP involves breaking complex tasks down into tiny, mechanical chunks that <a href="/things-that-take-no-talent">require no talent</a> ie. 1) Sit in your chair in a silent room, 2) load Rosetta Stone software, 3) Repeat Pashto phrases back to the computer for 1 hour, etc. Each of those could easily be done by a very stupid person, who would balk utterly if I commanded him to “Learn Pashto!”</li>
  <li>DP is repeatable, ie. you can come back tomorrow and learn more Pashto vocabulary using the same (sit » load software » repeat words) algorithm as you used today</li>
  <li>DP involves a tight iterative feedback loop, where good or bad outcomes are connected to your actions in near real time. For example, the Rosetta Stone software will grade your pronunciation as soon as you finish talking.</li>
  <li>DP is difficult</li>
</ul>

<p>In a way, DP is a method for standardizing disparate problem domains. Rather than discovering a new meta-method for improvements in each sphere of your life, you can try to make the problem fit a DP shaped mold. If you need to learn node.js for a project at work, you might read about DP and then try to approach the problem like this: </p>

<ul>
  <li>Find a practice problem that you can solve in Node
    <ul>
      <li>Goal = Use node.js to display the average temperature in London each day on a computer screen</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Break this goal into little chunks. Steps =
    <ul>
      <li>Learn to display “Hello World” on a computer screen</li>
      <li>Find a data source for the temperature. Maybe Her Majesty’s weather service, or weather.com?</li>
      <li>Learn to perform addition and division in Node</li>
      <li>Use addition and division operations at the same time to calculate the average temperature</li>
      <li>Employ each of the previous steps in a single program</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Scale up and repeat
    <ul>
      <li>Now show a timeseries plot of London’s temperature.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Carefully observe the code’s failures and successes. Make note of approaches that did and didn’t work for future use.</li>
  <li>Be prepared for difficulty</li>
</ul>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Growth Mentality]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/12/growth-mentality/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-12T22:06:36-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/12/growth-mentality</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Out of the box, you will suck at a lot of things. It is your job to regard this as a temporary state of affairs <em>that you can consciously take steps to fix</em>. </p>

<!--more-->

<p>If this blog can only convince you of a single thing, make it this one. It is vitally, crucially important that you avoid the stagnation mindset. View your present condition not as an end or event, but rather as the starting point for a process of improvement. Train yourself to reason about <em>skills that can be learned</em> instead of <em>aptitudes</em> or <em>talents.</em> Locating reverse gear in a standard-transmission Volkswagen in the dark? That sounds like a learnable skill that could be improved with careful practice! Juggling four beanbags at the same time, so as to entertain one’s children? Definitely a learnable skill. Persuading your boss to give you a raise? Often viewed as an aptitude/luck, but in fact eminently learnable.</p>

<p>In sports, in business, in academics, in the fine art of womanizing, and in matters of character, you must take steps to improve your skills, knowledge, and position. </p>

<p>But not just any steps—you need to find out the single canonically best way to improve in your discipline, and then focus your efforts on that. The <a href="/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/">deliberate practice</a> post talks more about that, and I encourage you to read it. But this post isn’t really about any specific meta-problem-solving algorithm. Rather, it is focused on the mindset of seeing <em>solvable problems</em> of design and implementation everywhere you look and <em>regarding your current reality as a starting point.</em></p>

<p><blockquote><p>kai · zen<br/>noun<br/>a business philosophy or system that is based on making positive changes on a regular basis</p></blockquote></p>

<p>Warning! This mindset will bring the haters out of the woodwork. Otherwise agreeable people, your friends, lovers, and acquaintances, will suddenly narrow their eyes and regard you with suspicion. People don’t like change, and they especially don’t like change that leaves them behind. They will try to tear you down, imply that things are perfectly fine as-is, and cast thinly-veiled aspersions upon the likelihood of your success. Be prepared to ignore this and keep going. Luckily, people have short memories, and in a few weeks or months, they will accept the new and improved you as normal. And after you iterate a few self-improvement cycles in front of them, they will have a <a href="http://www.engineerguy.com/white-papers/made-to-stick.htm">schema</a> for your kaizen and therefore look askance at you not quite so often as formerly.</p>

<p>When you commit to this growth mindset, it is scary for two reasons:</p>

<ol>
  <li>You are going to be wrong. </li>
  <li>You are going to admit that you are wrong (loudly).</li>
</ol>

<p>If you’re a millenial, that latter point is particularly terrifying. But stick with me—this is a solvable problem and we can sort it out. (See what I did there?) In fact, you will very likely learn to love the moment when you discover that you were wrong. Once your ego is out of the way, you can view the negatives in the training set as a shortcut to mastery—instead of getting unhelpful ambiguous feedback from the world, you have now learned what not to do, and can make changes accordingly to start dominating. </p>

<h2 id="an-example-from-sports-training">An example from sports training:</h2>
<p>A wide variety of skill levels are represented on the average childrens’ cricket team. The stronger, taller nine-year old bowlers have a seemingly unassailable advantage. And for a few seasons, it looks as though the scrawnier players are doomed to cricket careers spent on the sidelines of the pitch. </p>

<p>But if you spend enough time involved with childrens’ cricket, either officiating, spectating, or coaching, you’ll start to see a pattern. Those seemingly unassailable early-growth-spurt bowlers become accustomed to the trappings of effortless success. Their superior size, speed, and strength renders them complacent, and they learn that they don’t need to apply themselves to the business of sound fundamentals, skill building, or technique. Worse yet, these large, strong players tend to have a “biggest gorilla around” attitude, wherein they develop a know-it-all, senior-member-of-the-team persona. This persona invariably inhibits further technique growth and diminishes coachability.</p>

<p>Surround your pullquote like this {&#8221; text to be quoted &#8220;}</p>

<p>And a funny thing happens as time passes. Before long, the technical advantages of careful study, coachability, and the “I am a beginner” mindset have compounded. The large children, the former stars, are still performing at the same level of fundamentals as they were three seasons ago, and their output has risen slightly, perhaps linearly, as they develop musculature and coordination. But some of the little guys are starting to reach the “hockey stick” region of their player-development curve, and in the space of a few months they can develop into extremely performant players. Invariably, the most valuable players on an Upper Sixth form cricket team—around 18 years of age—are either A) in the 1% of most physically gifted athletes or B) extremely coachable former weaklings. Needless to say, the intersection of A and B is where great bowlers are made. But one cannot change one’s innate talents, and since this is a blog about self-actualization, it is best to focus on the latter case for all practical purposes.</p>

<p>At any rate, the moral of the story is that in childrens’ cricket and many other fields, dilligence and malleability trump inborn talent and static advantages. It behooves you to behave like the scrappy little guy, and to avoid at any cost the mentality and behavior of the stagnant former starring batsmen. </p>

<p>And by way of closing, might your humble correspondent suggest that you avoid flailing about, and instead carefully direct your efforts at self improvement, perhaps by reading the discussion of <a href="/blog/2014/11/14/deliberate-practice/">deliberate practice</a>?</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
