<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Administrative | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/administrative/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2014-11-29T20:11:10-05:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[What's the Point of This Blog?]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/whats-the-point-of-this-blog/"/>
    <updated>2014-11-29T19:48:24-05:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2014/11/29/whats-the-point-of-this-blog</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This blog serves a couple purposes.</p>

<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;m hoping to get new ideas by writing short essays, following Paul Graham&rsquo;s (persuasive) <a href="http://www.paulgraham.com/writing44.html">claim</a> that</li>
</ul>


<p><blockquote><p>&ldquo;Writing doesn&rsquo;t just communicate ideas; it generates them. If you&rsquo;re bad at writing and don&rsquo;t like to do it, you&rsquo;ll miss out on most of the ideas writing would have generated.&rdquo;</p></blockquote></p>

<!--more-->


<ul>
<li>I have strong opinions about a variety of topics, including but not limited to:

<ul>
<li>The growth mindset</li>
<li>Self improvement</li>
<li>Best practices for learning new stuff</li>
<li>Civil society</li>
<li>Capitalism, social control, and The Establishment (cue scary music)</li>
<li>Masculinity</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>


<p>In general, these topics are either boring or not socially acceptable in polite company, so I never get to discuss them. Maybe we can fix that here.</p>

<ul>
<li><p>I&rsquo;ve learned some solid truths in the past few years, mostly by trial and error, and it would make me happy if some younger guys found this and learned those truths the easy way.</p></li>
<li><p>Lastly, this blog functions as a journal of sorts. It keeps my ideas in one place for later reference (and might facilitate some looking-back-at-how-wrong-I-was/crow eating by an older and wiser me). Many of the posts that are written in a prescriptive tone were originally intended as reminders to myself. In fact, quite a few of them were literally handwritten (in abbreviated form) on sticky notes on my desk.</p></li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
