<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: First-principles | Bro Kaizen]]></title>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/categories/first-principles/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-10-07T19:55:11-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[bro_kaizen]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[A First-Principles Derivation of Ethno-Nationalism]]></title>
    <link href="http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2017/10/07/a-first-principles-derivation-of-ethno-nationalism/"/>
    <updated>2017-10-07T00:41:16-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://bro-kaizen.github.io/blog/2017/10/07/a-first-principles-derivation-of-ethno-nationalism</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[A civilization is neither a country's land and soil, nor its built environment of skyscrapers and bridges, nor its laws written on paper. Civilizations are always and everywhere made of *people.* And consequently, if you *remove* the people from a country, you will inevitably *remove* their civilization along with them. 

<!--more-->

## I. On the Composition of Civilization

Similarly, if you *replace* those original people with others, you inexorably *replace* the civilization itself. The land and soil will remain, and for a time also the buildings and perhaps even the law books. Maybe the country&#8217;s name will persist. But the *civilization* will be gone. 

Let&#8217;s conduct a thought experiment. Imagine a situation where the entire population of Japan disappeared from their islands, perhaps because a terrible disease rendered Japan uninhabitable. And the disease persists there such that no new people can take the departed Japanese&#8217; places. Would you ever say that &#8220;Japanese civilization continues in Tokyo?&#8221; Of course not &#8212; because *there are no Japanese people in Tokyo.* It&#8217;s just a bunch of buildings, not a civilization. The law books still exist in the law libraries, and the mountains and rivers are all precisely where they&#8217;ve always been. But that ineffable magic that makes a society has vanished. 

Now adjust the thought experiment slightly. Instead of merely removing the Japanese, replace them one-for-one with Sioux Indians from North America. Would you now say that &#8220;Japanese civilization continues in Tokyo?&#8221; Again, of course not. That would be a preposterous claim. Something would be happening on the islands we call Japan, and perhaps we could even call it a civilization, but it would certainly not be *Japanese* civilization. 

Let&#8217;s adjust the thought experiment further still, by replacing only N% of the Japanese with Sioux Indians. For N = 0% replacement, it&#8217;s obvious that the thing happening in the Japanese islands is inarguably *Japanese Civilization*. Conversely, at N = 100% replacement (aka the case above) it&#8217;s obviously *not* Japanese Civilization. As we increase N, we find a hybrid civilization, with some Japanese characteristics, and some non-Japanese characteristics. At some point, we&#8217;ll pass a critical threshold, what&#8217;s called in the layman&#8217;s literature a &#8220;tipping point,&#8221; beyond which Japanese civilization has ceased to recognizably exist as such. 

The critical premise of Ethno-Nationalism in all its incarnations is that the threshold value of N should be identified (noting it likely varies per-civilization) and not exceeded. Of course, some incarnations are more controversial than others. We&#8217;ve chosen Japan as an example here because in Japan, it&#8217;s a mainstream idea that Japan should remain substantially Japanese. And in fact even the smuggest and most sanctimonious social-justice types in New York and Seattle don&#8217;t particularly oppose this idea. Similarly, it&#8217;s quite rare to hear an objection to the idea that Libya or Ghana ought to remain Libyan and Ghanaian.

But if you swap Japan for a country in the White man&#8217;s homeland, you&#8217;ll suddenly meet terrifyingly virulent resistance from many quarters. We leave it as an exercise for the reader to examine why this is so.
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
